<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Hinc illæ lachrymæ. Or the impietie of impunitie. Containing a short, serious and most certain demonstration of the main (if not, only) rise and originall of all the grand grievances, and obstructions of piety and justice, over the whole kingdome. Together with a soveraign salve, and precious plaisture, for the unquestionable cure thereof (by Gods blessing) if it be seriously and seasonably applyed, according to direction herein, humbly prescribed. / By a faithful friend to the truth and a most humble servant to all the loyall and religious Presbyterian Members of Parliament.</title>
            <author>Gauden, John, 1605-1662.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 88 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85856</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G358</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E421_6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E540_16</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204669</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99864135</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99864135</idno>
            <idno type="VID">164904</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85856)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 164904)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 66:E421[6], 84:E540[16])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Hinc illæ lachrymæ. Or the impietie of impunitie. Containing a short, serious and most certain demonstration of the main (if not, only) rise and originall of all the grand grievances, and obstructions of piety and justice, over the whole kingdome. Together with a soveraign salve, and precious plaisture, for the unquestionable cure thereof (by Gods blessing) if it be seriously and seasonably applyed, according to direction herein, humbly prescribed. / By a faithful friend to the truth and a most humble servant to all the loyall and religious Presbyterian Members of Parliament.</title>
                  <author>Gauden, John, 1605-1662.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 29, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year. 1648. [i.e. 1647]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A "faithful friend to the truth and a most humble servant to all the loyall and religious Presbyterian Members of Parliament" = John Gauden.</note>
                  <note>Annotations on Thomason copies: "Decm: 23 1647"; the '8' in imprint date is crossed out (E.421[6]); "Jan. 30th" (E.540[16]).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Presbyterianism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Religious aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:164904:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>HINC ILLAE LACHRYMAE.</hi> OR THE Impietie of Impunitie.</p>
            <p>Containig a ſhort, ſerious and moſt certain Demonſtration of the main (if not, only) riſe and Originall of all the grand grievances, and Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions of Piety and Juſtice, over the whole KINGDOME.</p>
            <p>Together with a Soveraign Salve, and precious Plaiſture, for the Unqueſtionable Cure thereof (by Gods bleſſing) if it be ſeriouſly and ſeaſonably applyed, according to direction herein, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly preſcribed.</p>
            <p>By a faithfull Friend to the Truth and a moſt humble Servant to all the Loyall and Religious Presbyterian Members of <hi>Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>EZECHIEL 13.22.</hi>
               </bibl> With lyes, ye have made the heart of my people ſad, whom I have not ſadded, And ſtrengthed the hands of the wicked, that he ſhould not return from his wickedneſs.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>MAY. 18, 7.</hi>
               </bibl> We unto the World, becauſe of Offences, it inevitably will be that Offences come, but woe to that man <hi>(or thoſe men)</hi> by whom the Offences do come.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>GALAT. 1.7, 8.</hi>
               </bibl> There be ſome that trouble you and would pervert the Goſpell of Christ. But, though I, or an Angel from heaven <hi>(or one like an Angel, for pretended purity and Saint-ſhip)</hi> preach any other Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel <hi>(or broach any other damnable deſtructive opinions)</hi> than that which I have preached unto you, let him be accurſed.</q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed in the year. 1648.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:164904:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:164904:2"/>
            <head>The Impiety of Impunity.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen the Lord, the moſt righteous Iudge of the whole world, and the moſt potent and prudent Moderator of all things in heaven and earth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan, firſt, to ſettle the Common-wealth of <hi>Jſrael,</hi> and to give thoſe his people good <hi>Lawes,</hi> and holy and wholeſome <hi>Inſtitutions,</hi> which, <hi>if a man doe and perform he ſhall even live, ye happily, live, in them, Ezech.</hi> 20.11. He then alſo gave them ſpeciall Cautions and Commands to keep and doe them, as is moſt cleare, <hi>Levit.</hi> 19.15. <hi>Ye ſhall doe no unrighteouſneſſe in judgment, thou ſhalt not reſpect the perſon of the poore, nor honour the perſon of the mighty; but in righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe ſhalt thou judge thy neighbour.</hi> And remarkably excellent (for all that ſit in ſeates of judicature) is that, <hi>Deut.</hi> 1.17. <hi>Ye ſhall not reſpect perſons in judgment, but you ſhall heare the ſmall as well as the great; you ſhall not bee afraid of the face of man, for the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is Gods.</hi> So that (hence) it is evident, that it is not enough for a people to have good <hi>Lawes</hi> and pious and provident <hi>Precepts,</hi> but there muſt alſo be a ſpeciall care had to a juſt and impartiall judging of Gods people according to thoſe Lawes, neither to pervert or wreſt them (<hi>Deut.</hi> 16.19.) according to mens <hi>Schiſmaticall</hi> hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours; nor to ſlight or neglect them for want of a righteous and ſevere execution of them; which, indeed makes Magiſtrates and Iudges, but meere <hi>Scare-Crows</hi> in a Common-wealth, and juſt like the ſigne or picture of <hi>George on horſe-backe</hi> with his Sword bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſht and flouriſht over his head, but never ſtriking with it; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as it is the exact and impartiall <hi>execution</hi> of <hi>Lawes,</hi> indeed, which is the life and luſter of Laws, and the firme eſtabliſhment of States and Kingdomes. Now, then this being thus only in briefe hinted;
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:164904:3"/>now for application of theſe premiſes to our preſent purpoſe. It is moſt undeniably true, that (by Gods great mercy) <hi>England</hi> hath as good and wholſome <hi>Lawes</hi> and <hi>Ordinances,</hi> both <hi>old</hi> and <hi>new,</hi> for the well and orderly regulating of al things both in Church and State, I beleive, as any Nation in the World: Nay, may we not (with holy <hi>David</hi>) ſay moſt truly, <hi>God hath not dealt ſo, almoſt with any Nation under heaven, as with us, and as for his judgments, they have not known them,</hi> as we have, both in the <hi>power, purity,</hi> and <hi>plenty</hi> of them; O that we had hearts enough practically thankfull for ſo rich and rare a mercy! But, may not that queſtion bee put to too many of our <hi>Judges</hi> and <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi> yea, even in our High and Honourable <hi>Supreame Court of Parliament,</hi> which the foreſaid kingly Prophet <hi>David</hi> did put to the <hi>Judges</hi> of his dayes, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 58 1, 2. <hi>Do ye, indeed ſpeake Righteouſnes, O ye Congregations? Do ye judge uprightly, O yee ſons of men? yea rather, in heart and tongue, ye worke wickedneſſe.</hi> So, may not I bee humbly bold, in the bitterneſſe of my Soule, to ſigh out this very ſame moſt ſad complaint of the Prophet (not, as thoſe late audacious <hi>Incendiaries,</hi> thoſe <hi>Jeſuiticall-ſpirited</hi> and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring <hi>Maſters</hi> of <hi>miſrule,</hi> who plead moſt unjuſtly for <hi>Liberty</hi> (or rather for <hi>Licentiouſnes</hi>) of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> I mean thoſe ſpiritually proud <hi>Sectaries</hi> and fiery <hi>Salamanders</hi> of Contention, Maſter <hi>Iohn Goodwin,</hi> together with his moſt ſeditious brother <hi>Iohn Lilburne, Overton,</hi> and diverſe others of that rotten rout, unworthy the naming, who ſwelter and ſwagger, with their reſtleſſe <hi>ſpirits</hi> and <hi>pens,</hi> againſt any <hi>Authority, Dominions</hi> and <hi>Dignities,</hi> ſave only ſuch as themſelves would wickedly ſet up to pleaſe their own ſeditious and pernicious Palates: But, as the Lord, the moſt righteous Iudge, and only ſearcher of the hearts and reignes of his Children knowes, in the ſpirit of meekneſſe, ſorrow, and ſobriety) may not I (I ſay) too juſtly, thus complaine againſt ſome of our <hi>Parliamentary Judges,</hi> in theſe our dayes, and of theſe I meane (mainly, and ſpecially) di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe disaffected <hi>Schiſmaticall Members of both Houſes of Parliament,</hi> who (being got or crept in among our other moſt famous and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>Parliamentany Worthies,</hi> whom from my heart, I highly honour and love, but by what meanes they have thus crept in, I know not, but it were ſingularly worth the ſerious ſearch and Scrutiny to know how they came in, and by what right they ſit as <hi>Iudges</hi> and <hi>Senators</hi> there) who doe moſt unjuſtly and partially (for their <hi>Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes</hi> ſake, and other moſt unworthy <hi>Selfe-ayms,</hi> and Intereſts) wreſt the judgments and Ordinances of the Land, yea of the Lord God
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:164904:3"/>himſelfe, and accept the perſons of moſt bold blaſphemous <hi>Sectaries, Anabaptiſts, Antinomians, Anti-Scripturiſts, Seekers,</hi> and (who cloſely and craftily include and imbrace all thoſe others in their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomes) diſorderly and diſſembling <hi>Independents;</hi> whereby they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly ſtrugle in upholding theſe, to with-hold and hinder (if not totally to overturne, eradicate and ruinate) the glorious worke of our <hi>Parliamentary</hi> promiſed, yea our <hi>Covenant</hi> plighted thorough <hi>Reformation,</hi> eſpecially in matters of our <hi>Religion,</hi> and godly <hi>Church Diſcipline</hi> (for which I mainly complain and plead in this diſcou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe) calumniating and diſgracing it, with the moſt opprobrious titles, and injurious termes of a <hi>bloudy, tyrannicall,</hi> and <hi>Antichriſtian De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation;</hi> and moſt falſly and fraudulently magnifying (yea, even deifying) their owne ſandy <hi>Congregationall way</hi> with the ſpecious <hi>Epithites</hi> and <hi>Encomiums</hi> of <hi>Milkie-paths</hi> (forſooth) <hi>glorious wayes, Chriſts Kingdome</hi> and ſuch like moſt loud lying and eluding gloſſes; Thus, wilfully (I feare) forgetting that which the <hi>holy Spirit</hi> of God ſayes, by <hi>Solomon</hi> the wiſeſt King that ever was; <hi>Prov.</hi> 24.24, 25. <hi>He that ſayth to the wicked thou art righteous, him ſhall the people curſe, and Nations ſhall abhorre him. But, to them that rebuke him ſhall bee delight, and a good bleſsing ſhall come upon them.</hi> Now, that our ſlye and ſubtile <hi>Sectaries</hi> and <hi>Independents</hi> (every where) are moſt deeply dyed, even in grain, with this foule and faulty <hi>ſpot,</hi> which is not the <hi>ſpot of Gods Children,</hi> but (<hi>Deut.</hi> 32.5.) of a <hi>perverſe and crooked ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration,</hi> let theſe following teſtimonies, fallen out (beſides their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold former Calumnies and Slanders, by them caſt upon the pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Preſbyterian Church-Government,</hi> and upon the Reverend, and pious <hi>Paſtours</hi> and faithfull friends and furtherers of it, publiſhed in their moſt wicked printed Pamphlets, and recited by Reverend and religious Mr <hi>Edwards</hi> in the third part of his <hi>Gangrana, p.</hi> 200, 201, 202, 203, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) and whereof I my ſelfe, together with many other religious and ſubſtantiall <hi>Citizens of London,</hi> were eye and eare wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi>) be ſufficient to demonſtrate and make evident to any impartial and unprejudiced Chriſtian, or, that is not wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obſtinate and wilfully incredulous, which were as follow.</p>
            <p>I being (on <hi>Tueſday, Februarie</hi> 2. 1646. and on the <hi>Thurſday</hi> following, <hi>Febr.</hi> 5th. in the afternoon) at the <hi>Committe for Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints,</hi> to heare the examination of one <hi>Kiffin</hi> a Glover, a ſly and ſottiſh Mechanicall preaching <hi>Anabaptiſt,</hi> and one Mr. <hi>Knowles,</hi> another of his <hi>Anabaptiſticall</hi> brethren, which laſt, had caſt off his former regular <hi>Ordination</hi> in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as being
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:164904:4"/>ſinfull (forſooth, as himſelfe then confeſt) and had a <hi>pretended Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination</hi> from a true reformed-Church (as he falſly termed it) in a private <hi>Houſe,</hi> by a company of <hi>Sectaries,</hi> there diſorderly aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled: Together alſo with one <hi>Gorton,</hi> another <hi>Non-ſenſe Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſticall</hi> Preacher, forſooth, and a moſt notorious baſe fellow, and audacious Malefactor in <hi>New-England,</hi> who had there been fetter'd in Irons, and whipt, and was like to have been hang'd for his moſt impious and audacious blaſphemies and miſdemeanours; upon oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of the mentioning whereof, in that Court, I heard an emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Independent Gentl. of that <hi>Committee,</hi> ſay openly in the face of the Court, <hi>I (ſayes hee) ye may ſee how they begin already, what think ye, will they not do hereafter, if they get power and may be ſuffered?</hi> And with the ſaid <hi>Gorton,</hi> was then alſo examined one <hi>Patience</hi> a <hi>Botcher,</hi> or <hi>Tayler;</hi> ordained alſo (forſooth) to bee a Preacher, in a true reformed-Church (as he alſo falfly and fooliſhly termed it) in a <hi>Houſe</hi> in <hi>Bell-Alley</hi> in <hi>Colleman-Street,</hi> by the Saints, forſooth, of that Church, Men and Women (Hee-Saints and Shee-Saints, and all of them it ſeemes, Church-Officers with them) upon tryall of his gifts, by theſe Saints, as thus he alſo himſelfe confeſt. At the hearing of whom examined, my heart was (at the firſt) affected with no little joy and comfort, to heare and obſerve, even all along, the Chriſtian Courage, and godly Zeal of that ancient and pious <hi>Patriot</hi> Sir <hi>Robert Harlow</hi> religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and renowned <hi>Major Generall Maſſey,</hi> Colonell <hi>Hollys,</hi> Mr. <hi>Tate,</hi> Mr. <hi>Baynton,</hi> and ſome other worthy <hi>Presbeterian Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers</hi> of the <hi>Houſe,</hi> then preſent at this <hi>Committee</hi> (as formerly at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother ſitting, I obſerved the ſingular zeale of my moſt highly ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured good friend, Mr. <hi>Grimſtone,</hi> much honoured Colon. <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy,</hi> and others) both in their frequently and fervently ſpeaking and pleading for the <hi>Cauſe of God,</hi> then in agitation before them. But when I on the other ſide ſaw and obſerved, in this <hi>Committee,</hi> very many known and profeſſed <hi>Independents,</hi> to ſit as Iudges there, and too frequently and fiercely (me thought) to act and plead for, yea and to put words into the mouths of thoſe Delinquent <hi>Sectaries,</hi> and (though all of them were, I ſay, known adverſaries to our pious <hi>Presbyterian Church-Government,</hi> intended, as we ſtedfaſtly hope, by the <hi>better-part</hi> of the honourable <hi>Parliament,</hi> yet theſe I ſay) to ſit as Iudges there, and to ſpeake ſuch encouraging words (and that in open Court) to the <hi>Delinquents,</hi> and then alſo to have power to Vote on their behalfes; and contrawiſe alſo, to obſerve and heare
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:164904:4"/>them uſe ſuch diſcouraging carriages, and dishearting expreſſions to the honeſt and pious <hi>Covenant-engaged</hi> and <hi>Ordinance</hi> animated <hi>Proſecutors</hi> of the <hi>Offenders.</hi> This made me fetch a deep <hi>Sigh,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, as being much amazed at it, and I muſt confeſſe, my heart was very much daunted and damped with griefe to ſee and obſerve ſuch a moſt unequall and palpably injurious miſmanaging of ſo great and godly a work as we hoped and expected this would and ſhould have been unto us. And it was indeed unto me a wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and ſtrange <hi>Paradox</hi> of <hi>Prudence</hi> and <hi>Iuſtice</hi> (as I humbly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive) that the apparent and <hi>profest enemies</hi> of the <hi>Presbyterian-Cauſe</hi> and <hi>Reformation,</hi> ſhould thus ſit as <hi>Judges</hi> and <hi>Parties</hi> to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front us, and frown upon us, for our loyall, religious, and juſt act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings againſt ſuch crafty and accurſed <hi>adverſaries</hi> of the <hi>Truth.</hi> Which made me begin ſeriouſly to conſider with my ſelf, how im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probable (if not almoſt impoſſible) it was for us in ſuch a caſe and condition of times and things, ever to expect a full and free courſe or current of juſtice againſt them. And hereupon, indeed, my ſad thoughts began to reflect backward, and to think upon the <hi>by-paſt-times</hi> of the tyrannicall <hi>Prelates,</hi> when pious and peaceable <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſours</hi> were (under the names and notions of factious and Sciſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall) cited in their <hi>High-Commiſsion-Courts,</hi> and there judged by thoſe known enemies of their cauſes; where, indeed I confeſſe, they were all profeſt adverſaries (but here, our <hi>truly ſeditious</hi> and <hi>Schiſmaticall Delinquents,</hi> and the honeſt proſecutors of them alſo find an unhappy mixture of <hi>Foes</hi> with <hi>Friends</hi>) whereby though the pious <hi>Profeſſors</hi> themſelves could there find, indeed, neither expect any juſtice; yet the wicked <hi>Apparators</hi> and <hi>Perſecutors</hi> of thoſe true <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Servants</hi> of the Lord, were countenanced and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged by thoſe their <hi>Prelaticall</hi> Maſters, yea and liberally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded by them: But, here, in this <hi>Committee for Complaints,</hi> where the <hi>cauſe</hi> being far otherwiſe, the <hi>caſe</hi> is alſo in ſome ſenſe <hi>clean con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary,</hi> and (if I may be humbly bold to ſpeak plain Engliſh) in ſome reſpects, with us much worſe, and more unjuſt, when the moſt pernicious and audacious <hi>Schiſmaticall offenders</hi> are fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarly much countenanced and encouraged, and the honeſt and <hi>Covenant-Conſcientious Proſecutors</hi> of them are diſgra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, flouted, frown'd upon, yea and impriſoned for their pious pains, and religious actings for God and his moſt righteous <hi>Cauſe:</hi> whereby, I ſay, <hi>our Caſe</hi> is thus like to be far worſe than that of the <hi>Prelates</hi> dayes <hi>(comparatis comparandis)</hi> and our grievances, yea
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:164904:5"/>I ſay, our <hi>Soul grievances,</hi> ſo far (we fear) from being redreſſed, that they are like to be much more encreaſed, if this moſt unjuſt courſe of judicature ſhould (which God forbid) be continued, and that <hi>Sectaries</hi> be thus ſuffered (both in <hi>Parliament</hi> and <hi>country-Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittees</hi>) to ſit, as uncontroleable <hi>Iudges,</hi> who are ſo far from either doing or ſuffering juſtice to be done upon the moſt ſeditious and factious diſturbers of our pious Peace and unqueſtionable <hi>Truths</hi> of God, and of all godly eccleſiaſticall and civill <hi>Order;</hi> that they both countenace (at leaſt as much as in their <hi>power</hi> and <hi>policy</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts, and truly that's not little now adayes) and very greatly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage them in their unſufferable <hi>Schiſmaticall</hi> impundencies and blaſphemous impieties, both againſt <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man,</hi> and all under baſe and abuſive pretences of <hi>tenderneſſe of Conſcience,</hi> forſooth, and <hi>Christian Liberty</hi> to ſpeake and do whatſoever they liſt, without controle; otherwiſe, they cry out of <hi>Antichristian Perſecution.</hi> But mark here (good Reader) what wiſe King <hi>Solomon</hi> moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinently ſayes to this very purpoſe, even touching <hi>Impunity</hi> to be the <hi>grand cauſe</hi> of the great growth of <hi>Impiety,</hi> yea and of <hi>Impuden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi> alſo therein, <hi>Eccleſiaſtes</hi> 8.11. <hi>Becauſe ſentence againſt an evill work is not ſpeedily executed; therefore the hearts of the ſons of men is fully ſet in them</hi> (mark this notable and emphaticall expreſſion) <hi>to doe evill.</hi> And certainly (if ever) this <hi>Scripture</hi> is now adayes to the full confirmed, to the unexpreſſible griefe of our Soules be it ſpoken.</p>
            <p>But now to come to a more particular manifeſtation of the truths which I only in briefe have mentioned before, concerning the moſt irregular and extrajudiciall and inequitable carriage of things by our <hi>Sectarian Judges</hi> in the <hi>Court of the Committee for Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints,</hi> at <hi>Weſtiminster,</hi> to the palpable and apparent heartning and animating of the moſt notorious <hi>Schiſmaticks</hi> in their moſt blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous and impious pranks and practices; and to the moſt ſtrange, and almoſt incredible diſheartning (as much as in them is) of the pious <hi>Preſbiterian-Partie,</hi> from their juſt zeal and commendable activity in the <hi>Cauſe of GOD,</hi> and forwarding the work of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation.</hi> Witneſſe firſt, (therefore I ſay for confimation of theſe my affirmations) the moſt unequall and unwarrantable miſcarriage of things by ſome of the diſaffected party of the foreſaid <hi>Committee,</hi> at the examination of an old and bold blaſphemous <hi>Schiſmatick,</hi> commonly called the <hi>Chicken-man;</hi> who after this notorious <hi>Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> had made a repetition (whereunto he was commanded by the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:164904:5"/>
               <hi>Court)</hi> of his Sermon, forſooth, which he had Preached (or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther prated) in a private houſe, for which he was complained of, and when he had and a ciouſly delivered, even in the face of the <hi>Court</hi> divers very dangerous and moſt falſe opinions of his; yet was ſo far and free from puniſhment, or ſomuch as any bare diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (for ought we yet can heare or know) that one of the ſaid <hi>Committees</hi> was heard to ſay to one of his diſaffected brethren of this <hi>Committee,</hi> ſitting by, concerning this beggerly <hi>Chicken-man</hi> and his impious preaching; <hi>here is Gold in an earthen veſſell.</hi> And the ſaid <hi>Chicken-man</hi> himſelfe confeſſed (as will be teſtified) that he had 5<hi rend="sup">ſ.</hi> given him by ſome of the ſaid <hi>Committe,</hi> for his brave boldneſſe (it ſhould ſeeme) in thus affronting the <hi>authority of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</hi> Witneſſe likewiſe the great encouragement and counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancing of the <hi>Schiſmaticall</hi> impiety, and diſorderly audaciouſneſſe of thoſe two foreſaid <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> Mr. <hi>Knowlis,</hi> and <hi>Kiffin</hi> the <hi>Glover,</hi> at their examination forementioned, at the very begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning whereof an eminent diſaffected <hi>Member</hi> of the <hi>Committee</hi> ſtood up, and the <hi>Court</hi> being ſet, and the pious <hi>Chair-man</hi> in his place, <hi>bee ſpake very much (in the firſt place) to the</hi> Chair-man, <hi>and very affectionately in thoſe Schiſmaticks behalfe (whereby they might eaſily ſee and know before haud, they had at leaſt, one faſt friend in the Court) for a fair proceeding for them, in their examination;</hi> which I humbly conceive and verily beleeve was never denyed them, or otherwiſe intended toward them. And when <hi>Kiffin,</hi> in particular, was cloſely examined for his diſorderly and <hi>Schiſmaticall</hi> private preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (as never having been duly ordained thereunto) <hi>another</hi> of the <hi>Committee</hi> did in my ſight and hearing, even as it were check the religious <hi>Chaire-man,</hi> learned and much honoured Colonell <hi>Leigh,</hi> for juſtly endeavoring ſtrickly to examine the ſaid <hi>Delinquent.</hi> And this ſame Gentl. to the ſaid <hi>Anabaptists</hi> farther great encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, at the ſame time, apparantly juſtified (and that in the face of the Court) thoſe audacious fellowes, in their unordained and irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular preaching, even contrary to the <hi>Parliaments</hi> own <hi>Ordinance,</hi> uſing theſe words, or the like, in effect. <hi>That the Parliament did not intend, nor was it (as he conceived) the ſenſe of the Houſe, by that Ordinance, to hinder guifted-men from Preaching, this being one thing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> which many had fought, and ſpent their bloud, and ventur'd their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ives; but it was mainly to reſtraine Prelaticall and Ieſuiticall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reaching, which was a meanes to encourage the Cavaleers and Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ants against the Parliament.</hi> And when ſome of the honeſt and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:164904:6"/>religious <hi>Witneſſes</hi> gave in their teſtimony againſt the <hi>Delinquent,</hi> divers of the audacious and unruly <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> and other ſorts of <hi>Sectaries</hi> (whereof there were very many then in the <hi>Court,</hi> and ſo uſe to be, to affront and floute the <hi>Preſbyterian Citizens</hi> with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufferable ſcoffs and jeeres to their faces) fell a hiſſing and to loud laughing at the <hi>Witneſſe,</hi> to the great offence and diſturbance of the <hi>Court</hi> (which I my ſelfe heard and ſaw round about me) and noble <hi>Sir Robert Harlow</hi> moſt zealouſly and juſtly finding much fault with their ſo uncivill and unmannerly miſcarriage of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and expreſſing much diſpleaſure at it; <hi>One</hi> of the diſaffected <hi>Members</hi> of the <hi>Committee</hi> put a ſmooth jeere upon it, and ſaid, <hi>He conceived it was rather an acclamation or applauding of the witneſſe, than any diſparagement to him.</hi> Which, how likely <hi>hiſſing</hi> and <hi>laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> mixt together, can make up ſuch a ſenſe let any judicious man judge.</p>
            <p>Witneſſe, here alſo, that moſt licentious and illegitimate abuſe offered to the Liberty of the free-born Subjects and Citizens of <hi>London,</hi> in that palpable and moſt worthily puniſhable affront, and illegall impriſonment of thoſe 3. worthy, religious, diſcreet, and conſcientiouſly active Gentl. and Citizens of <hi>London,</hi> Captiane <hi>Wigmerpoole,</hi> Mr. <hi>Patrick Bamford,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Valentine Feige,</hi> who were all three, at one inſtant, moſt injuriouſly impriſoned, for only acting about a moſt honeſt <hi>Petition</hi> and <hi>Remonſtrance,</hi> which was to have been recommended by the <hi>Citizens,</hi> to the <hi>Lord Major</hi> and <hi>Common-Councell</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> to be, by them preſented to the <hi>Parliament,</hi> in the name of the whole City; and all this in ſuch a regular and modeſt manner, as had been by the <hi>Parliament</hi> it ſelfe ordered and preſcribed to them; yet notwithſtanding (I ſay) for this honeſt and orderly acting of theirs, theſe 3 aforeſaid Gentl. were impriſoned, by ſome <hi>Sectarian Parliament-Members,</hi> contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the intention, and order of <hi>Parliament,</hi> as that <hi>whole Committee for Complaints</hi> publikely acknowledged in <hi>Court,</hi> and worthy Sr. <hi>William Strickland</hi> (who then ſate in the Chair) proteſted againſt it as unlawfull, and none of his act or conſent. And thoſe <hi>Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall Members</hi> that commanded this moſt unlawfull impriſonment; being, ſince that, diſcovered who they are. And ſhall the <hi>Sectarian Party</hi> complain (as in <hi>Teuledaye's</hi> ſeditious cauſe they did) of wrong done to them, in the obſtructing and hindring their moſt pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and ſeditious petitions, and dare they moſt abuſively impeach 11. worthy <hi>Members</hi> of the <hi>Houſe of Commons,</hi> for this very thing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:164904:6"/>as one ſoule fault and offence againſt the ſubject; but indeed mainly, becauſe they are faithfull <hi>Preſbyterians?</hi> And ſhall not theſe <hi>Sectari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an-Members</hi> be much more juſtly impeached of moſt illegall and injurious infringement of the Subjects Libertyes (equally as pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious to us, as <hi>Parliament Priviledges</hi> are to them) and be inforced to give juſt repairations to thoſe injured Gentl. for their falſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment? And, truly, I much marvaile, that they themſelves are ſo ſilent, all this while, in this their owne ſo juſt vindication of themſelves therein. And (which, though here in the laſt, yet not in the leaſt place, but which deſerves to bee in the firſt and prime place, as being firſt acted. Witneſſe, in a ſpeciall manner, the moſt impious and ſlanderous abuſes caſt upon the whole <hi>Aſſembly</hi> of <hi>venerable Divines,</hi> both formerly, and ſtill to this very day (and that without all feare of puniſhment on the <hi>offenders</hi> part) in moſt ſcurrillous and ſcandalous <hi>Pamphlets,</hi> by the pernicious Pens of blattering and barking <hi>Sectaries</hi> of all ſorts: But more noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly in that moſt high affront, and great diſcouragement, yea and diſparagement too (as much as in them was) intended to be put upon the ſaid <hi>reverend,</hi> and <hi>religious Aſſembly,</hi> by the <hi>Sectarian diſaffected party,</hi> in the <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>Commons,</hi> it felſe, by whoſe meanes the <hi>Aſſembly of Divines</hi> were moſt unjuſtly denyed per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion by the <hi>Authority</hi> of that <hi>Houſe</hi> to vindicate their <hi>Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity</hi> againſt an <hi>all over</hi> moſt ſlaunderous <hi>Remonſtrance,</hi> publiſhed in print againſt the <hi>whole Aſſembly</hi> by 7 of the moſt <hi>Capitall</hi> and <hi>Cardinall Schiſmaticks</hi> of the ſame <hi>Aſſembly;</hi> yea, though our <hi>Divines</hi> had moſt earneſtly petitioned the <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>Commons,</hi> yet were deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this moſt juſt favour from them, and were, thereupon, inforced to fly unto the moſt honourable <hi>Houſe of Peeres,</hi> for juſtice therein, and, there, by Gods good providence, moſt honourably obtained it, to their unterminated and indelible honour and praiſe, be it ever mentioned. And truly (Chriſtian Reader) if theſe things were not too apparently thus, <hi>viz.</hi> That the very <hi>Fountaine</hi> and <hi>Spring</hi> of all the ſad and bad obſtructions of the work of <hi>Reformation</hi> were not at this <hi>Conduit-Head,</hi> the <hi>Parliament;</hi> and that all ſorts of <hi>Sectaries,</hi> and their <hi>Boulſterers</hi> and <hi>Abbettors</hi> (notwithſtanding all Petitions and Complaints againſt them) were not, <hi>There,</hi> ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſtrnagely countenanced and encouraged; how durſt <hi>Mecha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicks, Souldiers,</hi> and <hi>Troopers</hi> in the Army, &amp; al <hi>Sectaries</hi> both in City and Country, ſo audacioſly and diſorderly take upon them to Preach without <hi>Due-Ordination,</hi> yea and to <hi>re-Baptiſe</hi> men and women, youths
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:164904:7"/>and maids, ſo frequently and familiarly, yea and obſcurely too, naked in Rivers, and that in cold weather, ſometimes with great danger of death, yea death it ſelfe, in ſome, ſo plunged overhead and eares in the water? How durſt many, both <hi>Commanders</hi> and <hi>Common-Souldiers</hi> in the army (yea, that army of Saints, for ſooth, <hi>ſo magnified,</hi> and <hi>cryed-up,</hi> for <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Civilty</hi>) ſo audaciouſly in high contempt of the <hi>Authority</hi> of <hi>Parliament,</hi> ſcorn and caſt away <hi>Ordinances</hi> of <hi>Parliament,</hi> produced for the protection and ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guard of godly and grave <hi>Miniſters,</hi> abuſed, beaten, and with great violence kept out, yea and ſometimes pulled out of their Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſs by thoſe ſainted <hi>Souldiers</hi> and <hi>Commanders?</hi> Yea, how durſt ſome of them be ſo bold, ſo impious, ſo blaſphemous againſt <hi>God</hi> and his <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as <hi>(horreſco referens)</hi> to bring a <hi>Horſe</hi> into a <hi>Church,</hi> to piſs into the <hi>Font,</hi> and with that piſſe (in high and horrid con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of that ſacred <hi>Ordinance</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe for <hi>Baptizing of Infants</hi>) to baptiſe the horſe in the Font, to ſigne it with the ſigne of the croſſe, to have Godfathers and Godmothers for it, and to name it <hi>Baal-Eſau</hi> (an act alone, if there were nothing elſe in the Army, enough to bring <hi>Gods</hi> wrath upon them moſt deſervedly) all this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtrongly juſtified by reverend Mr. <hi>Edwards, Gangr. pt.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 17.</p>
            <p>Nay, more, How durſt that baſe and bold traitorly <hi>Tayler, loyce,</hi> ſo impudently, and independently (it ſeemd) aſſault (as we all know of late, he hath done) the Kings Perſon in his bed, together with his armed traiterous Troopes, and moſt audaciouſly wreſt and wring his Majeſty out of the Parliaments hands, forcing noble Colonell <hi>Graves</hi> to flye away, and ſo impriſoning both the King himſelfe and the Parliaments Commiſſioners in their <hi>Harpiean</hi> paws and power; And in all this their traiterous actings and proceedings, their Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, Sir <hi>Thomas, Fairfax</hi> to be ſilent, and at moſt, to plead igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance thereof, and (notwithſtanding that, now, he ſees and knowes it, yet) ſuffers that traiters head ſtill upon his ſhoulders, and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutes not Marſhall-Law upon him, and ſome of the other prime Actors therein (which, I humbly conceive, by the rules of Marti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all diſcipline, he might and ſhould have done) the beſt way, I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, to purge his own innocency therein, and to cleare his integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to the Parliament, and to make all honeſt men to believe he had no hand therein, and gave no conſent thereunto. And yet, in all this, I cannot but mightily admire and wonder at the moſt ſtrange ſtupidity, and inchanted beſottedneſſe of the Malignant party, alſo, that they ſhould be ſo bewitcht by that Hypocriticall and moſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:164904:7"/>Army of Saints, forſooth, as to believe that they doe all this in honour to the Kings Perſon and dignity, whereas, they and we all know tis one of theſe Schiſmaticks prime principles (as <hi>Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burne,</hi> and all his deſperate adherents hold and publiſh in print) ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly to caſt off Monarchy and Magiſtracy. And I my ſelfe can ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie that one of the principall Colonells now in the Army, and a Member of the Houſe of Commons, and one of them that had his hand in print with the others, that by name, impeached the eleaven Members: Yea, I ſay, one of the moſt ſmooth-mouth'd Saints in that whole Army, having not long ſince, had conference with mee in <hi>London,</hi> and I at that time pleading with him, in the behalfe of the King, profeſſing it was my minde and judgment, that all good and godly courſes were to be uſed to work His Majeſty (if poſſible, by Gods gracious help) to true repentance and godly reformation with us; but, hee anſwered me preſently, That the King was a a man of bloud, and muſt be brought to juſtice for it, unleſſe he could cleare himſelfe. And doe theſe men, then (thinke our Malignants) intend any good to the King or his poſterity. Yea, (to goe on) and were it not for our Parliament Sectaries, how durſt our audaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Sectaries</hi> and <hi>Schiſmaticks</hi> pen, print and publiſh (even almoſt without controle, I am ſure without juſt and mightily merited pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment in the moſt of them) ſuch baſe, blaſphemous and notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly ſeditious books, ſuch as lying <hi>Lilburnes</hi> baſe Pamphlets, <hi>Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wins</hi> abhominably blaſphemous <hi>Hagio Ma:</hi> againſt GOD and all ſound <hi>power of Godlineſſe,</hi> againſt the <hi>King,</hi> and the Lords and Commons in Parliament, to ſtirre up the hearts of the people (if it were poſſible for them, and that the over-powring hand of God did not moſt mightily and mercifully croſſe and confound their moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>villiſh and deſperate deſigne therein) to riſe up in rebellion againſt them all, and ſo to bring all things both ſacred and civile, into a moſt unexpreſſible and woefull <hi>Chaos</hi> and confuſion? which how neere they are come to it, at this time (by all the ſtrangely graſped power which the Army hath now got into their clutches) wee all ſee and ſtand amazed and wonder at. And, how durſt the (of late) degenerous <hi>Gentry</hi> of that unconquered County of <hi>Kent,</hi> who (for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly) began ſo bravely, but afterward I ſay, turned their backes ſo unworthily upon <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> as to endevour to bring that people into one of the greateſt and baſeſt <hi>Yoakes</hi> of <hi>ſlavery</hi> and <hi>ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytrary Tyranny</hi> that ever any people endured, or, indeed, could endure, <hi>viz.</hi> Not ſo much as to dare to grown out their griefes, no
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:164904:8"/>not in a modeſt way of petitioning for eaſe of them; and ſo to make that an accurſed <hi>leading-caſe</hi> to all the <hi>Counties</hi> and <hi>Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tees</hi> over the Kingdome? And, were it not that the Sectaries in the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and their nauſeons neutrall <hi>Sidemen,</hi> were ſo potent, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticke and confident to carry on any deſigne ſuitable to their ſelf-aymes and intereſts, eſpecially, their damnable <hi>Diana,</hi> an intolerable toleration of <hi>Liberty of Conſcience;</hi> how durſt a certaine company of them (in moſt high affront to the famous City of <hi>London</hi> (which hath deſerved ſo well of the <hi>Parliament</hi>) and apparent injury to their famous and faithfull late <hi>Lord Major, Alderman Adams</hi> in the time of his renowned Majoralty) ſodainly enter his houſe at 12. or 1. of the Clocke at night, forcing him out of his bed, at that time of the night, and (as it was generaly reported) ſearching his houſe, yea and his very pockets of his wearing cloathes, as if he had bin a very Traitor, and all this but only out of meer Chymaera's, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipts, and jealouſies of him, being a moſt pious and zealous Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian, but, they were not able to finde ought againſt him, to lay to his charge (ſuch was his intact integrity, and unſpotted loyalty) for which ſo injurious dealing with him, and thus affronting him in his peaceable houſe and bed of reſt, had he preſently clapt them up in priſon, in the City (as, tis believed, he might, they ſo illegal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aſſaulting him, the Cities ſupreme Magiſtrate) he had done moſt worthily, but we hope time will call them to accompt for this and the reſt of their moſt ingratefull dealings with ſo renowned and honourable Citizens, who have by their perſons, lives, bloud, and almoſt incredible ſummes of treaſure, (next under God) beene the main preſervers of the Parliament to this very day; yet, which hath, I ſay, with ſuch black and groſſe ingratitude, rewarded all their coſt and kindneſſe, by diſcountenancing and retarding their juſteſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, calling and counting their moſt famous and faithfull Petitions and Remonſtrances, ſeditious and candalous papers; and now of late eſpecially, abuſing the whole City (to pleaſe a rebellious Army) as touching their <hi>Militia,</hi> and by an Ordinance of the <hi>Sectaries</hi> and their Sidemen (for, none elſe, certainly would or did aſſent unto it) <hi>of both Houſes,</hi> condemning the Citizens moſt honeſt Petition, and neceſſitated <hi>Reingagement</hi> to ſtand to their Covenant, of high Treaſon, and the Authors thereof and Actors therein to bee <hi>Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors</hi> (to a moſt diſloyall Army) thus, making our ſacred <hi>Covenant,</hi> ſo ſolemnly commanded by <hi>both Houſes,</hi> taken over the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, a moſt dangerous ſnare unto us all, and hereby bringing all
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:164904:8"/>honeſt and Conſcientious <hi>Covenanters</hi> into a moſt <hi>intricate Laby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth</hi> and dangerous <hi>Dilemma,</hi> viz. <hi>That, if they will not (in the preſent and moſt eminent emergency of the</hi> Church <hi>and</hi> States <hi>great danger) act according to their</hi> Covenant, <hi>they are accurſed, as forſworne</hi> Perjurers <hi>to their great God;</hi> And if they doe act according to it, they are proclaimed <hi>Traytors,</hi> to the <hi>Parliament</hi> or <hi>Army,</hi> rather. <hi>O inauditum &amp; infandum-nefas!</hi> And if theſe things were not thus, how durſt thoſe <hi>mercenarie-Scriblers</hi> of the weekly <hi>Diurnalls,</hi> and that botching <hi>Moderate-Intelligencer</hi> (as now adayes he tearms himſelfe, being by his own feare and ſhame whipt out of his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer title, the <hi>Parliament-Scout,</hi> forſooth, and the reſt of their bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen-fac'd brethren, the other mendacious <hi>News-mongers,</hi> the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted hirelings and pandors of <hi>Independents,</hi> and all other ſorts of <hi>Sectaries,</hi> how durſt theſe, I ſay, ſo audaciouſly <hi>ſtricke</hi> with the fiſt of <hi>ſlander,</hi> one week; and <hi>ſtroake</hi> with the <hi>fingers</hi> of <hi>flattery,</hi> the next weeke, the untainted <hi>integrity</hi> and reſplendent <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation</hi> of our moſt loyall and loving <hi>Brethren</hi> of <hi>Scotland,</hi> as they have done? making their incomparable <hi>fame</hi> and <hi>faithfullneſſe</hi> to ſtand or fall, every weeke, at the reverſion of the beggarly <hi>ſhreds</hi> of their botching <hi>pens</hi> and <hi>pleaſures;</hi> yea notwithſtanding, that thoſe our moſt deare <hi>Brethren</hi> had heretofore requeſted the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> to puniſh, or, at leaſt, to reſtraine or ſilence their inſolencies, in thus uſing and abuſing them, as indeed they do to all others of the <hi>Preſbiterian-party,</hi> on whomſoever their ſaucy humours pleaſe to ſpit upon, and all this without the leaſt appearance of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or reſtraint? Yea how, I ſay, durſt all theſe, and more than theſe moſt groſs and grievous <hi>enormities</hi> and foule <hi>deformities</hi> in <hi>Government</hi> thus boldly break-out among us, were it not that ſuch a company of diſaffected <hi>Members</hi> did thus ſit <hi>Iudges,</hi> as aforeſaid in the <hi>Parliamentary Committee for Complaints</hi> at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> yea and in the very <hi>body</hi> it <hi>ſelfe</hi> of the <hi>whole Parliament,</hi> both <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons,</hi> whether, all the <hi>Schiſmaticks</hi> and <hi>Sectaries</hi> over the whole Kingdome, both <hi>City</hi> and <hi>Country,</hi> doe too well know all their buſineſs are at the laſt and utmoſt exigent to be tranſacted and heard, and where they are ſure ſuch a company of their <hi>faſt friends,</hi> ſhall ſit as their <hi>Iudges,</hi> and therefore whatſoever <hi>Complaints</hi> are made againſt them, they do but laugh in their ſleeves at us, and contemn all our threats or menacings of them, as being well aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured that by theſe their <hi>Patrones</hi> meanes, either our complaints ſhall be totally ſtifled, as <hi>abortive-Embrio's;</hi> or if heard, ſo pinch't
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:164904:9"/>and pin'd with moſt <hi>tedious-tyrings</hi> and <hi>languiſhing delayes,</hi> that wee weere (for the moſt part) better ſit ſtill in ſilence, and groan under our grievances, than torture and turmoile our ſelves with <hi>remedileſſe wreſtlings,</hi> to little or no purpoſe. Which things (and many more to theſe effects, too tedious here to be cited) being thus, alaſſe, to what end is all this noiſe of our ſo hoped and long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed-for <hi>Reformation,</hi> in the ſerious <hi>Suppresſion</hi> of <hi>Blaſphemies, Schiſmes,</hi> and <hi>Errours,</hi> and in the ſubſtantiall <hi>ſettlement</hi> and <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleting</hi> of our promiſed <hi>Presbyterian-Government?</hi> Why do the honeſt-hearted, active and religious <hi>Covenant-engaged</hi> Citizens of <hi>London,</hi> thus toyle and tyre themſelves, day by day, with too lank and empty hopes, and pining expectations of redreſſe of al theſe <hi>high diſhonours</hi> of almighty God, and <hi>great grievances</hi> on the hearts and conſciences of his people, in bringing ſeditious <hi>Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> as <hi>Delinquents</hi> and bold <hi>Affronters</hi> of the Supreme Court of the Kingdome, the <hi>Parliament,</hi> to this <hi>Committee,</hi> where they continually find ſuch a <hi>company</hi> of their <hi>Jndependent</hi> friends ſitting as <hi>Iudges</hi> of thoſe <hi>Offenders</hi> whom theſe very <hi>Judges</hi> (as being known <hi>Parties</hi> with them in <hi>Judgement</hi> and <hi>Opinion</hi>) do ardently love and like, yea hug in their hearts, and as much as poſſibly they can, do labour to maintain, countenance, commend, and encourage in their moſt erroneous, yea blaſphemous and ſeditious practiſes. witneſs, blaſphemous <hi>Beſt,</hi> that bold and abominable Beaſt, indeed, not worthy to live; ſeditious, lying <hi>Lilburne, Overton,</hi> and ſuch like turbulent traſh; who (though ſome of their perſons are (I confeſs) or have bin (but, with no little ſtruggling) only impriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, where truly, they are (juſt as the <hi>Romiſh Jeſuites</hi> were) bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter maintained, than abroad, yet) are ſtill ſtrangely permitted to foment and ſcatter in ſcurrillous Pamphlets, their moſt blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous opinions, and pernicious practiſes; yea, and are moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily and wickedly juſtified and commended, even by very many of our <hi>Sectarian diſaffected Members</hi> of <hi>Parliament?</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſſe, what's become, now adayes, of the priſtine <hi>power, dignity, equity, gravity,</hi> and awefull and lawfull <hi>ſeverity</hi> of our former ancient <hi>Engliſh-Parliaments?</hi> Heretofore it was as terrible, cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minall, and puniſhable to ſpeak (eſpecially to write) againſt the juſtice, acts and edicts of the <hi>Parliaments</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> as to ſpeak or write treaſon againſt the <hi>Perſon,</hi> or <hi>Crown</hi> of the <hi>King.</hi> But that now, in theſe our dayes, every baſe and ignoble <hi>Sectarie</hi> ſhould be thus permitted preſumptuouſly to ſpeak, write and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:164904:9"/>preach againſt it, and that, with the moſt falſe and ignominious acrimony of ſpirits and pens, that poſſibly may be, I am confident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſwaded, it is not to be paralell'd by any by-paſt ages or Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories. What? hath amiable <hi>Aſtraea</hi> quite forſaken our <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> on earth, and is impartiall and Majeſticall juſtice no where to be found? for if not there, where ſhall we find it? Shall ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, peaceable and humble hearted <hi>Preſbyterians</hi> be thus, enforced (which God forbid, and which, as yet, we heartily abhorre) to feare and ſuſpect that thoſe audacious and contumelious <hi>aſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> and (we hope and believe) moſt ſlanderous <hi>Calumnies</hi> of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious lying <hi>Lilburne</hi> and the reſt of his rebelliouſly rayling and ſcribling <hi>Comrades,</hi> are like to prove too true <hi>aſſertions?</hi> and all becauſe of ſuch delatory obſtructions, yea, even vitious violations and infringements of the courſe and current of juſtice, and the Subjects <hi>hereditary juſt Liberties,</hi> equally as precious to <hi>them,</hi> as <hi>due priviledges</hi> are to the <hi>Parliament:</hi> God forbid, I ſay, we ſhould have continued cauſe to feare it. But, if it be otherwiſe; How, then, comes it to paſſe, that the <hi>wheeles</hi> of the glorious worke of a deeply deſired, and moſt duely promiſed and long expected <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation</hi> turne and roule ſo ſlowly and heavily? How is it, that <hi>Votes</hi> and <hi>Ordinances</hi> for the advancement of pure <hi>Religion,</hi> the <hi>power of godlineſſe</hi> and our <hi>Covenanted Preſbyterian Church Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline,</hi> are ſo extremely delayed, and with ſuch admired difficulty, even as it were, but, <hi>pedetentim,</hi> or <hi>guttatim,</hi> obtained and produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced; and when any doe come forth, how is it that they are ſo void of expected and neceſſitated ſtrength and corroboration for their work intended (or rather, by ſome, but deceitfully pretended? But only by reaſon (as it is <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ox populi,</hi> which men commonly ſay, is <hi>Vox Dei.</hi>) that thoſe disaffected <hi>Members</hi> eſpecially of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable <hi>Houſe of Commons</hi> doe ſo craftily and vigilantly watch their owne <hi>ſeaſonable opportunities</hi> (by the improvident and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, I confeſſe, neceſſitated <hi>abſence,</hi> and thereby <hi>paucity,</hi> too of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, of the honeſt and truly pious and zealous, <hi>Preſbyterian party,</hi> either to null them, or at leaſt, to delay, obſtruct, and invalidate them, and to make them of little or no ſolid uſe, when they come forth unto us? Wherein, alſo, (which fetches a moſt juſt and deep figh from my ſoule) the known <hi>Independents</hi> are not a little, backt and abetted (a moſt foule ſhame to be ſpoken of them) <hi>by many</hi> who formerly (at leaſt in ſhew) were clearely for us; but, now a-dayes (though we beleive; not properly principled the <hi>Schiſmeticall-way</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:164904:10"/>yet) are mightily byaſſed, wheeled and blown about (I know not by what unhappy <hi>fate,</hi> or <hi>flate</hi> of <hi>winde,</hi> unleſſe, as I heare and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a <hi>Golden-ayre</hi> or <hi>Silver-blaſt</hi>) in voting and acting for the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> almoſt, on all occaſions; who they are, <hi>I</hi> ſpare to name, though I could, many of them, <hi>Et digito monſtrare quod his est;</hi> but, they themſelves beſt know, and are conſcious to their own hearts of this their great evill of ſo unworthy <hi>doubling Tergiverſation;</hi> and though we pitty and pray for their <hi>Soules,</hi> yet they may and muſt be aſſured, we look upon their <hi>perſons</hi> with very <hi>ſore-eyes</hi> and <hi>ſowr faces.</hi> Great and grave <hi>Senators</hi> of <hi>England</hi> (I ſpeake to the truly pious <hi>Preſbyterian party</hi> thereof in <hi>both Houſes</hi>) I beſeech you, for the Lords ſake, think often and earneſtly on that faithfull (for, <hi>hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and earth ſhal periſh before one jot or title of Gods Word ſhal not come to paſſe</hi>) yea think upon, even with trembling, that fearefull threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Lord our God, <hi>Jerem.</hi> 48, 19. (which alſo, I have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly made ſerious uſe of in another piece of mine, entituled, <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices Plea.</hi>) <hi>Curſed be he that doth the worke of the Lord negligently</hi> (or, <hi>deceitfully,</hi> as ſome tranſlations notably render it) and <hi>curſed is he that withholdeth his ſword from bloud.</hi> Yea, I ſay, from bloud, when the Lord requires it, even the bloud of <hi>Blaſphemers,</hi> and bloudy <hi>Malignants,</hi> eſpecially in theſe our late and moſt lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble lawleſſe Wars, on the Royall Party; for then, to ſpare, is ſo farre from <hi>Piety</hi> or <hi>pitty,</hi> that it is egregious <hi>impiety</hi> to God and our ſacred Covenant, and <hi>Diabolicall cruelty</hi> againſt men; yea and a moſt dangerous <hi>hazarding</hi> of the ruine of your own lives, if not of <hi>Parliament, State,</hi> and the whole Kingdome, as <hi>Ahab</hi> for ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <hi>Benhadad,</hi> and <hi>Saul</hi> for ſparing <hi>Agagg,</hi> found it too true; and we may juſtly feare the like, when ſuch (whom God hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to death) live ſo confident (and that, not without cauſe) that the bitterneſſe of the feare of death is over paſt with them; and all by reaſon of the ſtrange <hi>Impunity</hi> of the bloudy <hi>Impiety,</hi> even of grand <hi>Offenders</hi> of all ſorts to this very day. There was a time (I muſt and doe ingeniouſly confeſſe) when the great (and, then very juſt) apologie and plea of our great and wiſe <hi>Parliamentary</hi> Maſter-<hi>Builders,</hi> why the work of <hi>Reformation,</hi> in <hi>Religion</hi> (for I deſire mainely to harp upon this ſtring, as the <hi>ſummum,</hi> though I will not ſay, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nicum neceſſarium</hi>) and ſpeedier building of <hi>Gods Houſe, Church-Diſcipline</hi> went not on more ſoundly and ſeriouſly, was, That the prudence and providence of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment muſt, firſt, ſee to the very <hi>being,</hi> before the well being of the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:164904:10"/>Kingdome which then indeed, was in continuall hazard of ruine and deſtruction by the great hoſtile powers on the Kings party; True, I eaſily and willingly grant this: But, now that the Lord hath moſt graciouſly baniſht thoſe our great and juſt feares, hath like duſt, diſpell'd our enemies, and given us <hi>opportunity</hi> (even ever ſince the ruine of Sir <hi>Iacob Aſhleys</hi> forces, and the rendition of <hi>Oxford</hi>) to build our own houſes in moſt ſweet ſecurity (and which we doe indeed, with <hi>both hands,</hi> but ſcarcely care to build Gods Houſe with <hi>one hand</hi>) O what, now hinders this beſt and moſt bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed worke? but, onely and unqueſtionably, theſe <hi>Parliamentary Schiſmaticks,</hi> theſe our meere pretending Maſter <hi>Builders,</hi> who prove indeed, the <hi>main-molesters</hi> of it? And, dare they indeed, call and count themſelves Maſter-<hi>Builders,</hi> and yet, ſtill, are the <hi>principall cauſes</hi> that Gods houſe muſt either lye waſt (as much as in them is) as being moſt unwilling (ſome of them) that we ſhould have any <hi>Government at all;</hi> or at beſt, now and then permit it to be patch't up with ſuch poore peices (as I toucht before) as rather amaze us with <hi>ſorrow</hi> to ſee, than animate us with any juſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to enjoye; whereof, I ſaid before, truly, I know no grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ground, or unqueſtionable cauſe to complaine (next to our groſſe ingratitude to God for ſo great a good as is <hi>Opportunity,</hi> now ſo long and ſo fairly offered us, but ſo looſly and lazily, if not lewd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly abuſed by us) than the intollerable (I had almoſt ſaid the inexpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able) <hi>impiety</hi> of the <hi>impunity</hi> of our unſufferable <hi>Schiſmaticks</hi> and <hi>Sectaries,</hi> eſpecially the admitting &amp; tollerating of men diſaffected to Church diſcipline, at the <hi>Fountain head,</hi> whereby all the ſtreams of <hi>juſtice</hi> and <hi>equity,</hi> thence iſſuing into City or Country, are la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentably poyſoned and polluted (a thing moſt worthy of unexpreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible puniſhment) and thus ſuffering <hi>Independents</hi> to ſit in ſuch prime places of <hi>Iudicature,</hi> and in <hi>Parliamentary,</hi> and Country Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tees, to the moſt ſtrange and ſtrong obſtruction and impeding of all our hopes or happineſſe from our moſt renowned <hi>Parliament,</hi> in generall, even the pious <hi>Preſbiterian-party</hi> thereof in both the moſt Honourable Houſes. Well, though theſe our diſaffect <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenders</hi> ſmooth up themſelees, and wipe their lips with an <hi>All is well with them;</hi> yet let them give mee leave to tell them one thing' to their juſt ſhame and ſorrow of Soule (if it may be) and that is; what a <hi>Heathen Prince</hi> hath pronounced againſt them, and tis backt alſo with <hi>Scripture authority</hi> and approbation; <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>honeſt-hearted King</hi> (of a Heathen,) King <hi>Darius,</hi> into
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:164904:11"/>whoſe heart, the Lord having put a reſolution to forward the building of <hi>Gods Houſe</hi> at <hi>Ieruſalem; Ezra,</hi> 6. Which work had been much oppoſed and impeded by the enemies thereof, yet, now I ſay, the King having reſolved that the work ſhould be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly ſet upon, and that none ſhould hinder it; the Text ſayes, <hi>ver.</hi> 11. <hi>He made a Decree that whoſoever ſhould go about or endia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to alter the Kings word, therein, the timber of his houſe ſhould be pull'd down, and a Gibbet ſhould be made thereof, and he to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed and hanged thereon; and that his houſe ſhould be made a jaxe, or dunghill, for this;</hi> even for daring to be ſo bold and impious as to offer to hinder the work of building of <hi>Gods Houſe.</hi> Mark this, O all ye <hi>Schiſmaticall-ſpirits,</hi> who, now adayes, ſo impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly and audaciouſly have ſo long and lewdly endeavoured to hinder the building of <hi>Gods Houſe,</hi> among us in <hi>England,</hi> even the glorious worke of <hi>Reformation</hi> in <hi>Religion,</hi> the ſettlement of the <hi>purity of Doctrin,</hi> and of the <hi>godly order</hi> and <hi>holy harmony</hi> of <hi>Church-Diſcipline.</hi> Hear it, I ſay, and tremble at it, and bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſham'd to heare a <hi>heathen-King</hi> ſo zealous for God (and you to be ſo cold) and ſo juſtly to pronounce your deſerved puniſhment; and take heed leaſt the Lord, the righteous judge (if too long and impenitently provoked by you) even <hi>for this,</hi> this great Sin of thus impeding &amp; oppoſing the bleſſed work of a <hi>thorough Reformation</hi> among us be moſt ſeverely revenged on you. And let me tel you al my dear brethren in general, both one &amp; another, and my ſelf too; never let us think tis poſſible that our temporall affaires of full trading, paying of the Kingdoms debts, eaſe of exciſe, and other tedious taxations, freedome from fears of new wars and commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions among our ſelves, the totall disbanding of our Armies, diſmantling of Garriſons, and ſueh like deſired nationall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts ſhall thrive and proſper or anſwer our hopes and expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſo long as <hi>Religion</hi> in its <hi>power</hi> and <hi>purity</hi> is ſo ſlighted, Gods faithfull and painfull <hi>Miniſters</hi> are ſo wickedly denyed, not only honourable, but even competent maintenance, and are, beſides, ſo ſcorned and abuſed, and ſo long as <hi>Gods Houſe, Church-Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline,</hi> is ſo ſtrangely neglected and delayed, and all ſorts of <hi>Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, Erronrs, Hereſies,</hi> and moſt blaſdhemous <hi>Opinions</hi> are with ſuch accurſed and moſt impious impunity permitted among us, and eſpecially, I ſay, that horrid and kingdome confounding ſin of, thus, moſt fearfully violating our <hi>ſacred</hi> and <hi>ſolemn Covenant</hi> with our God, wherein, with deep atteſtations and proteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:164904:11"/>holding up our hands and lifting up our hearts to the high God of heaven, we vowed the utter ruinating and extirpating of all thoſe forementioned ſores, evills, and plague provoaking crying-crimes, yea, and whatſoever elſe was contrary to the <hi>power of Godlineſſe.</hi> Touching which <hi>Covenant,</hi> heare me but one word more (ô all ye of the <hi>Schiſmaticall generation,</hi> in generall) concerning your moſt unconſcionable and double dealing, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luding of us therein alſo, and then I ſhall haſten to the <hi>maine thing</hi> I ayme at in this diſcourſe, which is, that having ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuouſly and evidently layd open the heart grinding and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <hi>Sore</hi> and <hi>Core</hi> of the kingdomes preſent and preſſing ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row; I may alſo humbly make bold to tender the <hi>application</hi> of a <hi>Plaiſture,</hi> which (I humbly conceive) is moſt likely (by Gods bleſſing) to make an undoubted comfortable cure thereof; but, to the thing in hand.</p>
            <p>In the dayes of rare Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> of ever bleſſed memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and ſo along, to later times, wee all know, or have heard, how the crafty <hi>Romiſh Ieſuits,</hi> having found by long experience, that their tying up of the Conſciences of their <hi>Popiſh-Proſelytes</hi> from taking the <hi>Oath of Supremacy,</hi> and from receiving the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the Lords Supper</hi> with us <hi>Proteſtants</hi> (whom, you know, they called and counted <hi>Hereticks</hi>) proved a great pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice to the progreſſe and growth of their great deſigne, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall Papall-Monarchy:</hi> at laſt, they grew ſo cunning and craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that, for the advancement and propagating of the <hi>Catholick Cauſe</hi> (as they call'd it) they would give diſpenſations, (by the <hi>Popes</hi> indulgences) to take that <hi>Oath,</hi> and to <hi>Communicate with us,</hi> in the <hi>Lords Supper</hi> alſo, if they were put unto it, rather, I ſay, than to hinder their other dark and devilliſh deſigne. And is it not juſt thus with our palpable and <hi>Jeſuiticall</hi>-Spirited <hi>Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendents and Sectaries,</hi> that <hi>generation of Iuglers</hi> (if ever there were any in the world) now adayes among us: I mean mainly the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile <hi>Seducers,</hi> and learned <hi>Ringleaders</hi> of them; for, was there not a time (and that, not long time agone) when their <hi>novell</hi> and moſt <hi>nauſeous upſtart-Schiſme</hi> beganne, firſt, to riſe and grow up among us; that, O, then, for an <hi>Independent,</hi> a <hi>Separatiſt,</hi> or <hi>Sectary</hi> to be put to the taking of our <hi>ſacred and ſolemn Covenant,</hi> O, it was moſt tart and terrible, and would by no means be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured by them, but they ſtartled at it, and flew from it, as from a hideous <hi>Hobgobling,</hi> or a <hi>Noli me tangere.</hi> But, now, of later
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:164904:12"/>times, and in theſe our more moderene dayes, they alſo having like the <hi>Ingling Ieſuits</hi>) craftily and cunningly found by practice and experience, that this <hi>Bolt</hi> was like to ſhut them out of the <hi>Parliament, Conutry-Committees</hi> and other <hi>eminent, gainfull, grace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,</hi> and <hi>over-awing places,</hi> both <hi>Martiall</hi> and <hi>Majeſteriall:</hi> they now, therefore (juſt, I ſay, like the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi>) for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagation of <hi>their Cacolick Cauſe</hi> alſo, I meane, <hi>Tolleration</hi> of <hi>All-Religions,</hi> and diabolicall and accurſed <hi>Liberty of Conſcience, aliàs,</hi> moſt prophane <hi>Libertiniſme;</hi> doe moſt diſſemblingly, falſly and fraudulently uſing the ſaid <hi>Sacred Covenant,</hi> as thoſe <hi>Jeſuits</hi> did the <hi>Sacred Scriptures,</hi> only as a <hi>Noſe of wax,</hi> or a <hi>Saylers Breechs,</hi> to help them in a <hi>ſtorme,</hi> or at a <hi>dead-lift</hi>) give <hi>ſelfe-diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation</hi> of <hi>Liberty</hi> to their <hi>Conſciences</hi> to ſubmit to the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king thereof, as well, and readily (to ſee to) as the beſt of us all, but, ſtill, with the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> old tacite-trick of <hi>Equivacation</hi> or <hi>men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall-Reſervation,</hi> taking it in their <hi>own-ſenſe,</hi> as moſt malevolently hating the <hi>litterall</hi> and <hi>genuine ſenſe</hi> thereof, and the poſitive and plain <hi>intentions</hi> and <hi>ends</hi> of the <hi>Parliament</hi> in generall, in the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant;</hi> as is, and long hath been apparent by their practiſes and profeſſions alſo both by word and pen, among us, not only in the <hi>Parliamentary</hi> and <hi>Country-Committees,</hi> but alſo, and moſt eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in the <hi>Army,</hi> where, moſt Inſolently and audaciouſly (as was toucht before) the <hi>Commanders, Officers,</hi> and <hi>Souldiers</hi> ſlight, reject, and ſcorn all <hi>Ordinances</hi> of <hi>Parliament,</hi> yea and the very <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant</hi> it ſelf, as it relates to <hi>Church-Government,</hi> eſpecially, and ſuppreſſion of <hi>Errours, Schiſmes,</hi> and <hi>Blaſphemies;</hi> yea not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that ſome of them pretend they have taken the <hi>Covenant,</hi> which muſt needs ſhew and aſſure us moſt undoubtedly in what <hi>ſenſe,</hi> and with what <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and to what <hi>ends</hi> they tooke it. The ſerious conſideration whereof makes me, here alſo, to fetch a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother <hi>deep ſigh</hi> for his Excellency Sir <hi>Tho. Fairfax,</hi> who of late, hath not a little overclouded and eclipſed the former radiant luſtre, and moſt ſpecious ſplendor of his (then) juſtly merited Fame and Honour, both by ſome late ſtrange miſcarriages in the Army in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, and alſo in ſo improvidently, and (doubtleſs) inſnaredly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting and entertaining, as his chief <hi>Chaplains</hi> for the Army, two dangerous and audacious <hi>Soul-ſeducing Schiſmaticks,</hi> as Mr. <hi>Dell,</hi> &amp; Mr. <hi>Saltmarſh,</hi> together with their bold &amp; bluſtring brother <hi>Peters,</hi> who are moſt pernicious &amp; peſtilent inſtruments to infect &amp; poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon the <hi>whole Army,</hi> if it be poſſible, with their ſeditious and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:164904:12"/>
               <hi>Doctrins:</hi> by which deceitfull deſigne of theirs, (I ſay) forementioned in <hi>thus</hi> taking the <hi>Covenant,</hi> they moſt <hi>Satanically</hi> keep-up, and drive-on their owne hopefull and underhand miſcheivous <hi>Machinations,</hi> and thereby alſo mightily moleſt, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct and retard, almoſt all our pious <hi>Preſbyterian-Actings</hi> accor: ding to our <hi>Conſcience</hi> and <hi>Covenant,</hi> as the fear of the Lord (whoſe vowes are upon us) do moſt importunately command us, and our fervent and deeply obliged love to <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Peace</hi> doth conſtantly conſtraine us. And thus wee ſee (to our <hi>ſad ſighing,</hi> indeed,) that no bands, nor bounds will hold or keep in theſe <hi>vild</hi> and <hi>wild Beaſts,</hi> but that moſt craftily and unconſcionably they break through all, and we have now (therefore) but <hi>one on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly way</hi> (under God alone) which is the laſt and maine thing I aime at in this diſcourſe, to help our ſelves out of the tearing and ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring troubles of theſe <hi>Bryers</hi> and <hi>Brambles,</hi> our <hi>Sectaries</hi> and <hi>Schiſmaticks;</hi> and that (I humbly conceive) is <hi>only this,</hi> and it is backt alſo with a freſh and experienced pregnant example among our ſelves, ſome few years paſt, which is, as followeth.</p>
            <p>There was (as we all well remember, at the beginning of this preſent <hi>Parliament</hi>) a great Complaint (and that, not without great and juſt cauſe) againſt <hi>Popiſh Lords</hi> and <hi>Prelates,</hi> ſitting in the <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>Peeres,</hi> and of rotten-hearted <hi>Malignant Members</hi> in the <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>Commons,</hi> who, in thoſe times, mightily mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſted and obſtructed the moſt waighty and great affaires of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and ſo conſequently perturbed the good of the whole kingdome, eſpecially, then alſo, in matters of <hi>Religion,</hi> and due execution of <hi>Iuſtice</hi> upon <hi>offenders:</hi> whereupon the moſt famous and ever to be honoured and renowned City of <hi>London</hi> bravely began to Petition the <hi>Parliament</hi> for the expulſion of them out of <hi>both Honſes,</hi> and immediately thereupon, almoſt all the <hi>well-affected Counties</hi> of the kingdome followed their worthy exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and moſt eagerly and earneſtly fell a petitioning againſt them, and continually came flocking up to <hi>London</hi> to the <hi>Parliament</hi> in moſt numerous and mighty multitudes, to that purpoſe, yea and ſo importunately preſt their deſires therein, till at laſt, by Gods wonderfull providence, and the <hi>Parliaments</hi> moſt favourable ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance of their Petitions, and (ſo far, then from calling or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counting it a breach of <hi>Priviledge</hi> of <hi>Parliament,</hi> that) they gave them all great thanks for their <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Zeale</hi> therein: And all theſe things thus concurring together ſtrook (as it was apparent)
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:164904:13"/>ſuch terror and amazement into the hearts of the <hi>Popiſh-Lords, Prelates</hi> and <hi>Malignants</hi> in <hi>both Houſes,</hi> that ſpeedily upon it (partly by the <hi>Prelates</hi> own remarkable pride and folly, and part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by an univerfall <hi>Conſcience-accuſing</hi> fright and terrour at theſe things) <hi>both Houſes</hi> of <hi>Parliament</hi> were moſt admirably freed of them; and all things, thereupon, preſently after, were carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on moſt proſperouſly, and with ſingular ſmooth ſucceſſe, to the great comfort and univerſall high content of the whole king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, (and ſo continued a long time after) untill theſe preſent crafty <hi>Sectarian Mombers</hi> unhappily crept into the <hi>houſe</hi> of <hi>Commons,</hi> and others have ſince been poyſoned by them. And have not We (my deare <hi>Preſbyterian Brethren,</hi> for, to you, now I apply this my main and moſt earneſt deſire) in theſe our dayes, as great and juſt cauſe (conſidering all I have already ſaid before, and much more that might be ſaid therein) as ardently and earn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtly to complaine, proteſt, and petition againſt ſome <hi>diſaffected Lords</hi> in the <hi>Houſe of Peeres,</hi> and againſt many <hi>Independent Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers</hi> in the <hi>Houſe of Commons,</hi> who (next to our own ſins) are the main, if not only, reſtleſſe <hi>Remora's,</hi> and moſt dangerous di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbers and delayers, yea mockers and deluders of our <hi>Covenant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>engaged Reformation,</hi> to Gods moſt high diſhonour, the moſt juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly incenſing of his devouring-wrath againſt us, and the deepe heart-wounding griefe and ſorrow of all the truly pious and peaceable <hi>people</hi> throughout the whole kingdome, by reaſon of their hopes thus unhappily damped and delayed, yea, I ſay, jeered and abuſed by thoſe <hi>Sectaries</hi> and <hi>Schiſmaticks</hi> in the <hi>Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons.</hi> Slight not (I beſeech you, my dear <hi>Preſbyterian-Brethren,</hi> both in City and Country) this my ſerious, and I hope ſeaſonable advice, by ſupine <hi>ſecurity</hi> in regard of the preſent ſeeming <hi>ſere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> of things, which hath been the bane of many famous and flouriſhing <hi>States</hi> and <hi>Common-weales;</hi> and yet (all things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered) we have little cauſe to conceit ſo of the preſent times. But, if they were ſo, yet know that I have read, long ſince, in <hi>Plutarch's Lives</hi> of a Governour of <hi>Thebes</hi> or <hi>Athens</hi> (if my memory much faile me not) to whom a faithfull friend of his ſent a <hi>Letter</hi> wherein was the diſcovery of a dangerous plot againſt him and his City, which was intended to be attempted on him that very enſuing night on which his Letter came to him the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate evening before to have prevented the danger of it, had it been timely taken: But he (being a deboyſt drunken <hi>Prince,</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:164904:13"/>notwithſtanding that the meſſenger told him his Mr. deſired the ſpeedy reading of it, and return of his anſwer) preſently put the Letter into his pocket, and only returned this anſwer; <hi>Res ſeriae ad craſtinum; Waighty matters to morrow.</hi> But, that very night the <hi>Deſigne</hi> was ſet upon, his enemies ſuddainly brake in upon him, ſlew this <hi>Prince</hi> in his bed, and ſurpriſed his City. Take heed timely, therefore, I ſay, and beartily pray you, my deare <hi>Brethren,</hi> of ſlighting this my coun ſell; our danger is, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly, very great, and I know not how neare it is (yea and who knowes what a day or a night may bring forth) though for the preſent, things ſeeme faire and cleare about us, as here you heard it in this foreſaid pertinent and applicable example. The <hi>King,</hi> himſelf <hi>(Proh dolor)</hi> ſtands out ſtill (and for my part, I cannot much wonder at him, therein, he being ſo mightily ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated thereunto by <hi>Sectaries</hi> and <hi>Schiſmaticks</hi> who pleading for <hi>Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> ſtand out boldly againſt the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and will uſe what kind of worſhip and ſerving God they pleaſe, yea and are extremely connived at, and to lerated therein: And why may not <hi>King Charles</hi> alſo plead for and be permitted the <hi>Liberty of his Conſcience,</hi> and be tolerated to have his <hi>Prelaticall Chaplains</hi> (as now alſo the <hi>Sectaries</hi> in the Army have already begun pretty fairly to give the King all this, and promiſe and pretend much more, till they have their wills of him) and allowance of his <hi>Common-Prayer Booke,</hi> and refuſe to be directed, in <hi>Gods worſhip,</hi> by our <hi>Directory,</hi> and reſuſe to hear our pious preachers, as well as our <hi>Sectaries</hi> and <hi>Schiſmaticks,</hi> who familiarly reſuſe both, yea, almoſt, all of ours; running into <hi>houſes</hi> and <hi>corners</hi> to practiſe what they pleaſe in matters of <hi>Religion?</hi> Why may not <hi>King Charles,</hi> I ſay, expect <hi>thus much liberty of Conſcience,</hi> and, as <hi>I</hi> ſaid before, be, thus, hardned by <hi>our meanes</hi> to ſtand out ſtillmoſt ſtifly againſt us; beſides, <hi>Malignant-Royaliſts</hi> grow thick and numerous within our City and adjacent Countries round about us; <hi>bloody<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minded Anabaptiſts,</hi> &amp; ſuch like ſeditious <hi>Schiſmaticks,</hi> as cruelly as craftily, yea as vigorouſly as viruently do drive on their deſignes among us, eſpecially that of intolerable <hi>Toleration,</hi> and accurſed <hi>Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> againſt all godly <hi>Government</hi> and religious <hi>Order,</hi> wherein the moſt deſperate <hi>Atheiſts</hi> and <hi>Malignants</hi> (for the preſent) joyne and combine moſt eagerly with them; yea, our own hoped freinds, within us, grow mightily diſconetnted,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:164904:14"/>and mutinouſly-minded (witneſſe <hi>Smithfields</hi> late firy-uproare at the ſtrange miſcarriage of things in the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued taxations on the poorer ſort of people; and thou, ô loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all <hi>London,</hi> the Kingdomes moſt famous and magnificent <hi>Metro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polis,</hi> art in as great danger of ſuddain diſtreſſe, as ever, if occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fion (which the Lord in his great mercy forbid) be miſcheivouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly offered, thy grandeſt <hi>Guard</hi> (under God) the City <hi>Militia,</hi> being for the greateſt part of it (notwithſtanding all thy petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oning about it) even to this day (according to that <hi>Apologue</hi> of the poor Sheepes Maſtives committed to the keeping and cuſtody of <hi>Wolves</hi> and <hi>Foxes</hi>) I mean, in known <hi>Sectaries</hi> and notorious <hi>Schiſmaticks</hi> and <hi>Neutralls</hi> hands and commands, in whom thou canſt not with any cleare ſafety truſt or confide. And therefore againe and again, I humbly and heartily beſeech you, whom it, thus, mainly concernes, timely to looke about you, and to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed, as you tender your lives, Wives and Children, Peace and Proſperity; yea, your <hi>All</hi> that is moſt precious to you, even your <hi>pure Religion</hi> eſpecially, your <hi>ſacred Covenant, Countries Liberties</hi> and juſt <hi>Freedomes;</hi> and ſpeedily take ſome honeſt, lawfull, and lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable importunate courſe by Petitioning, &amp; ſoliciting even with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out denyall, for the timely calling into the <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>Commons,</hi> of all the pious and loyall <hi>Presbyterian Members,</hi> and eſpecially of the inſufferably abuſed, becauſe moſt injuriouſly and ſlander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly accuſed 11. <hi>Members,</hi> if they be not come in already, and for the ſerious expunging and expelling of known and pernicious pragmaticall <hi>Sectaries</hi> out of <hi>both Houſes of Parliament,</hi> as being the maine, if not only cauſes (as I have moſt abundantly ſhewn) of all our preſent and moſt preſſing, yea oppreſſing <hi>fears,</hi> and growing and groaning <hi>Calamities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But, here, if any object (as, indeed, it hath been ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected to me already, upon occaſion of this very motion of mine, in private) that, though Sir, wee acknowledge your counſell is good &amp; pertinent to our condition; yet, we beleeve tis not (now) ſo feazable and ſeaſonable in regard of the times and the generall diſaffectedneſſe of moſt men, and the preſent policy and power of the <hi>Independents</hi> in the <hi>Parliament</hi> and elſe-where?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> To all which I anſwer, firſt, who drave out the <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh-Lords, Prelates,</hi> and other <hi>Malignant-Members</hi> (farre more firmly faſtned and rivetted in among us, even by a Law, although
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:164904:14"/>
               <hi>Such</hi> (which <hi>Independents</hi> are not, as <hi>Such</hi>) both in <hi>Parliament</hi> and in all other parts of the Kingdome, than theſe our <hi>Parliamentary Jndependents</hi> are, or, <hi>I</hi> truſt, ever ſhall or can be) who, I ſay, thruſt and threw theſe out of <hi>both Houſes</hi> of <hi>Parliament?</hi> Was it not the Lord God himſelfe, by his ſpeciall bleſſing on the una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimous confluence of importunate Petitioners, proteſting againſt them from all parts of the Kingdome? Even the Lord our God, who is <hi>yeſterday, and to day, and the ſame for ever,</hi> and can any thing be impoſſible for him to bring to paſſe, who, within theſe ſix yeares laſt paſt, hath all along, done, almoſt, all things mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culouſly for us, which we knew not how to have done for our ſelves? Take but this one example hereof; did not the Lord be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond our expectation (even to our juſt admiration) make the <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates</hi> themſelves (in a ſpeciall manner) by their proud <hi>Protestati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> againſt the <hi>Parliaments</hi> juſt proceedings, and their <hi>Petitioning</hi> to the <hi>King</hi> for his protecting of them againſt the power of the <hi>Parliament</hi>) to overthrow and throw themſelves out of the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> even into impriſonment in the <hi>Tower of London?</hi> And are not our <hi>Sectaries</hi> of theſe dayes, think you, as ſpiritually, yea and carnally proud and ambitious too as ever the <hi>Prelates</hi> were in their generation? and are they not every way as pernicious and peſtilentiall to Church and State, and many of them moſt illegally and abuſively elected and ſhuffled in to be <hi>Members</hi> of the <hi>Houſe?</hi> Secondly, for our great, yea, exceeding great encouragement here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, hath not the Lord (upon occaſion of the late <hi>ſolemn Faſt</hi> over the whole kingdome, againſt <hi>Hereſies</hi> and <hi>Schiſmes,</hi> voted in <hi>Parl. Feb.</hi> 4, 1646, and religiouſly performed and kept accordingly <hi>March</hi> 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, then next enſuing) put into the harts of the moſt reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious and renowned <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons</hi> in <hi>Parliament,</hi> to renew, &amp; as I may ſay, revow, and publiſh to the whole world (to Gods high honour, and our unexpreſſible comfort) their cordiall and zealous deteſtation of <hi>Hereſies, Schiſmes,</hi> and <hi>Blaſphemous Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> together with their religious reſolution peremptorily to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed agaidſt them; and for fuller ſatisfaction herein, I will give the <hi>Reader,</hi> their one words, in that moſt excellent <hi>Ordinance</hi> of theirs, worthy to be ingraven by us in fair <hi>Characters of Gold;</hi> which were, as followeth.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="ordinance">
                        <head>
                           <hi>Die Jovis, Febr.</hi> 4, 1646.</head>
                        <head type="sub">An <hi>Ordinance</hi> of the <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons</hi> in <hi>Parliament</hi> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſombled,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:164904:15"/>concerning the growth and ſpreading of <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, Hereſies,</hi> and <hi>Blaſphemies,</hi> ſetting apart a day of <hi>publik Humiliation,</hi> to ſeeke Gods aſſiſtance for the ſuppreſſing and preventing the ſame.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>THE Lords and Commons aſsembled in the Parliament of England having entred into a ſolemn-Covenant, to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, ſincerely, really and conſtantly the Reformation of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in Doctrine, Diſcipline, and Worſhip, and the extirpation of Popery, Superſtition, Hereſie, Schiſme, Prophaneneſſe, and whatſoever ſhall bee found contrary to ſound Doctrin, and the power of godlyneſſe; and having found the preſence of GOD wonderfully asſiſting us in this cauſe, eſpecially ſince our engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in purſuance of the ſaid Covenant: Have thought it fit (leaſt we partake in other mens ſins, and thereby be in danger to receive of their plagues) to ſet forth this our deep ſenſe of the great diſhonour of God, and perillous condition that this kingdom is in, through the abominable blaſphemies</hi> (mark their zealous expreſſions here) <hi>and damnable Hereſies vented and ſpread a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad therein, tending to the ſubverſsion of the faith, contempt of the Ministery, and Ordinances of Jeſus Christ: And as we are reſolved to imploy and improve the utmost of our power that nothing be ſaid or done againſt the Truth, but for the Truth; ſo wee deſire that both our ſelves, and the whole kingdome may bee deeply humbled before the Lord, for that great reproach and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt which hath been cast upon his Name and ſaving Truths, and for that ſwift destruction which we may juſtly feare will fall upon the immortall ſoules of ſuch who are, or may be drawne away by giving heed to ſeducing Spirits. In the hearty and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der compaſsion whereof, Wee the ſaid Lords and Commons doe order and ordaine that</hi> Wedneſday <hi>being the</hi> 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
                           <hi>day of</hi> March <hi>next, to be ſet apart for a day of publick Humiliation for the growth and ſpreading of Errours, Hereſies and Blaſphemies, to bee obſerved in all places within the kingdome of</hi> England, <hi>and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:164904:15"/>dominion of</hi> Wales, <hi>and town of</hi> Berwick, <hi>and to ſeek to God for his direction and aſsiſtance for the ſuppreſſion and preventing the ſame. And all Miniſters are hereby enjoyned to publiſh this preſent Ordinance upon the Lords day preceeding the ſaid</hi> 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
                           <hi>of</hi> March.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>See, hence, then may dear <hi>Preſbyterian Brethren,</hi> firſt, as I toucht before, if here be not ſingular encouragement unto you all in Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Country, to ſet ſeriouſly and ſpeedily upon this worke of modeſt and lawfull petitioning, as a foreſaid. Secondly, whether you are not moſt likely to receive kind acceptance, in ſo doing, and thanks for your paines and care therein. And thirdly, (if the <hi>Parliamentary Independents</hi> hinder not, as they are moſt likely to be the main, if not only, obſtacles therein) what unqueſtionable good &amp; deſired ſucceſs (as by this excellent Ordinance may eaſily be gathered) is likely to follow thereon. And fourthly, and laſtly, conſider from all the foreſaid premiſes, thus, now put together, whether all truly pious <hi>Proteſtants</hi> and <hi>Presbyterians</hi> over the whole kingdome have not as great and juſt cauſe to bend all their zeale and combined power of Petitioning aginſt the <hi>Sectaries</hi> and <hi>Schiſmaticks</hi> in <hi>Parliament</hi> (as the unqueſtionable cauſes of the great growth of all the <hi>Errours</hi> and <hi>Schiſmes</hi> among us; and as the moſt unhappy obſtructers and hinderers of the moſt long and zealouſly deſired building and ſettlement of the <hi>Preſbyterian Church-Government)</hi> as ever they had againſt <hi>Papiſts, Prelates,</hi> or <hi>Royall-Malignants?</hi> Which, if they ſee not, certainly they are wilfully blind, or if ſeeing, yet are baſely content, willingly, to yeeld to a moſt ignominious and ſlaviſh <hi>ſecurity</hi> and <hi>Laodicean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luke-warmneſſe</hi> to the unexpreſſible miſery that inevitably accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panyes the being juſtly ſpued out of Gods preſence and protection of love, by moſt lewdly allowing a moſt abhominable <hi>Tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of all religions, and ſo by an unqueſtionable conſequence of having no religion among us, and then alſo no God to helpe us. O, then, that it would pleaſe the Lord to put into the hearts of his honeſt and heroick Servants both in City and Country, now againe, moſt ſtoutly and ſtrenuouſly to ſhew their godly zeal and faithfull fervour of Spirit againſt thoſe enemies of our <hi>Covenant</hi> in this the Churches as great neceſſity and importunity, as ever it was in, with a joynt and unanimous conſent (as then they moſt happily and honourably did, and that with ſingular approbation and commendation of <hi>both Houſes of Parliament,</hi> and with deſired
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:164904:16"/>ſucceſſe too) to petition <hi>Both Houſes</hi> (in a warrantable, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt, fair, and befitting manner) for the removeall of the perſons of ſuch <hi>Parliamentary Independents</hi> out of their <hi>Houſes,</hi> as are the known fautors and favourers of all <hi>Schiſmaticall Covenant-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temners</hi> and <hi>Ordinance violaters,</hi> in reference to their contempt and obſtructing of the <hi>Preſbyterial Church-Government</hi> and <hi>power</hi> of <hi>godlyneſſe,</hi> even as perniciouſly and impiouſly (though more <hi>clandeſtinely</hi> and <hi>craftily</hi>) as ever the <hi>Popiſh Lords, Prelates</hi> or <hi>Malignants</hi> formerly were in their way; and therein moſt invin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cibly to endeavour the juſt exonerating of our ſoules of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes great and groaning <hi>ſpirituall grievances</hi> (the beſt way of all others to remove all our <hi>temporall diſturbances</hi> alſo) in the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufferable abuſes both of God and man among us, even the intole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable growth and ſpurious ſpreading of <hi>blaſphemies, hereſies, er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours,</hi> and <hi>ſchiſmes,</hi> together with the moſt abhominable <hi>impunity</hi> of the <hi>Broachers</hi> and <hi>Abettors</hi> of them, and for the holy and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py compaſſing and completing of one of the maine ends of our <hi>ſacred Covenant</hi> with our God, and with our moſt loyall and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving brethren of <hi>Scotland,</hi> namely, the ſolid and ſubſtantiall ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the <hi>Preſbyterian Church-Diſcipline,</hi> according to the word of God, and the example of the beſt <hi>Reformed-Churches.</hi> And, O that it might pleaſe the Lord, (who has the hearts of all men in his hands, and who can moſt eaſily turne them as the Rivers of water) to put into the hearts of our moſt renowned, noble, and precious <hi>Patriots,</hi> the unbyaſſed and honourable <hi>Preſbyterian</hi> friends of <hi>Truth</hi> and pious <hi>Peace,</hi> in <hi>Both Houſes</hi> of <hi>Parliament,</hi> who (cordially and chriſtianly caſting away all ignoble <hi>ſelfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeking aymes</hi> and <hi>interests</hi>) do religiouſly and conſcientiouſly cohere and correſpond, with ſound and ſettled judgements and reſolutions, to ſet up <hi>Chriſts kingdome,</hi> according to the <hi>Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall inſtitution</hi> in Gods word, to be happy and honourable means (for the more ſmooth and certaine carrying on of this ſaid bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed buſineſſe) to purge (if it bee poſſible) <hi>Both their Houſes</hi> in general, and inparticular, of al <hi>Committees,</hi> from ſuch incompetent and unequall judges as <hi>Sectaries</hi> and <hi>Independents</hi> are (who ever they be) from ſitting in ſuch <hi>ſeates</hi> of <hi>Iudicature,</hi> to hear, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rule, vote and determine ſuch waighty <hi>Cauſes,</hi> as are matters of <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Church-Reformation,</hi> as, wherein, they themſelves are ſo faulty and offenſive, yea devoted enemies to the <hi>Church</hi> and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:164904:16"/>
               <hi>Children</hi> of God, in poynt of <hi>Godly-Government</hi> and <hi>Church-diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline:</hi> wherein, that the Lord, the great God of wiſdome, the only <hi>guider</hi> of every good <hi>action,</hi> and the only <hi>giver</hi> of every good <hi>gift,</hi> would direct and erect the hearts of our truly pious <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary Patriots</hi> and ſound <hi>Preſbyterian Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons,</hi> with profound wiſedome, impregnable fortitude of Spirit, and invincible Chriſtian Courage, impartially and efficaciouſly to vote, act, and execute (in purſuance alſo of their moſt excellent and religious <hi>Ordinance</hi> againſt the <hi>growth</hi> of <hi>damnable errours</hi> and <hi>blaſphemies,</hi> forementioned) in the firſt place, to remove thoſe ſorely offenſive <hi>rubs</hi> and <hi>Remora's</hi> out of their <hi>Houſes,</hi> which thus have and doe (and till they bee removed, unqueſtionably will) moſt ſadly interrupt, impede and retard the ſomuch and ſo long deſired glorious work of <hi>Reformation,</hi> it is, and ever ſhall be a ſpeciall part of my moſt ſerious and inceſſant prayers: That, ſo, this being at length holily and happily effected, <hi>Iudgement may run downe in our ſtreets like waters, and Righteouſneſſe as a mighty and ſtrong ſtreame.</hi> That, ſo, our God may [in Chriſt] take plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in us, and delight to doe us good, all our dayes, and to our ſucceeding <hi>Poſterity</hi> after us, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>A Post-ſcript.</head>
            <p>CHriſtian Reader, I have thought fit (in this laſt place) to deſire thee to take ſerious notice (but not without a moſt deep ſigh from thy Soul) that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the <hi>Parliament</hi> intended (as we then hoped) to have done ſome great and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable work, for the juſt impeding of the growth of <hi>blaſphemous Errours, Schiſmes,</hi> and <hi>Hereſies</hi> among us, as is moſt abundantly evident by that moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Ordinance of the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>March,</hi> 1646, forementioned; yet (notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that <hi>Ordinance,</hi> and the ſolemn day of <hi>Humiliation</hi> kept over the whole king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome the 10th. of <hi>March</hi> following) nothing hath been done therein, ever ſince, which is now above 5. Moneths paſt; but, contrariwiſe a moſt foule and filthy greater growth and increaſe of them, in all parts and places of the kingdome, without the leaſt controul or reſtraint by any authority. O conſider, I beſeech thee (good Reader) in the feare of the Lord, what a horrid and hideous face of moſt abhominable hypocryſie and diſſimulation does this neglect therein repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to the Lord our God, and the whole world, unto our everlaſting indelible ſhame! And, vvhence, my Chriſtian Brethren, can you poſſibly conceive this moſt black ſin hath its riſe and originall, but mainly, if not only, from the <hi>Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> in our <hi>Parliament,</hi> who, as we have apparently ſeen, all along, have, without all queſtion, moſt ſtrongly and ſtrangely, and yet moſt craftily and cunningly croſt and cruſht all motions and means of carrying on this or any other waighty work of <hi>Reformation</hi> among us? <hi>And will not our God be avenged on ſuch a genearati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as this? And, ſhall they proſper, ſhall they eſcape, or ſhall they be delivered that do ſuch things, and that (thus) break their Covenant with their God?</hi> Ezekiel, 17.15, 16.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
